I'm sure you've interacted and had
plenty of of people women or not come up
to you and say I've tried to grow my
glutes I've tried I've tried it's not
worked are there any themes that have
popped up over those years and those
interactions of kind of most common
mistakes that they've been making in
other words people have been like I've
been asked this for a year it's not
working what am I doing wrong that's why
trainers have a job that's why you know
as of now personal trainers have job
security because it's so hard to do on
your own something's wrong A lot of
times it's the effort they're putting
forth they think they're training hard
but they could really do five more reps
if they really wanted to at the end of
the set a lot of times they're
sabotaging themselves because God
trainers around the world when they hear
this are going to be nodding their head
um men and women do both do this they do
it differently women will want to
combine and this will piss women off if
they hear this clip but they want to
combine weights with yoga Pilates
spin everything else and they'll say
well why why oh your heart isn't
important your heart health oh it's not
important to be flexible yes but uh you
have to prioritize so if you want
hypertrophy and you want glutes to grow
and you're doing all this extra exercise
and you're not really training when
recovered and you're not prior you're
not you're so busy trying to fit in all
your in yeah six balls in the air you're
trying you got to you got to train at
the right I like to think about it make
if if I said you got to and you got to
give yourself every opportunity to PR
what are you going to do you're going to
make sure you got a good night of sleep
you're not going to go do an hour of
cardio before you go try and do that
lift try to hit a bench PR you're going
to eat the right amount just the right
amount the right foods that agree with
you before your workout the right time
some people like to eat an hour before
some people like to train like fasted
but like you're going to you're going to
show up feeling good you had your
pre-workout a half an hour before your
coffee or whatever makes you gives you
the best chance and that's what you got
to do day in and day out for lots of
years and what I see is when you're just
squeezing in your workout at the end of
the day when you're already stressed and
you have already and then you're just
going through the motions y um you're
not going to grow like maximally you
might see some results and then too much
variety too much program hopping um
trying to do every exercise I love all
the exercises trust me and my gym for I
love quads and and hammies too so it's
hard cuz in my gym I've got H hack squat
machine the pendulum squat machine leg
presses Smith machine the V squat like
I've got it all what do I do you know I
I I want to hit quads sometimes you're
like I've been so distracted I haven't
done squats in a while and you're going
okay I got to get back to squats oh I
also have belt squats I have all the and
yeah they're all amazing and they
transfer to each other which is cool
sometimes you take your focus away same
thing with hamstrings I've got all every
leg curl machine I've got plate loaded
45 degree hyper selectorized 45re hyper
now you don't even have to grab a
dumbbell you just hold on to something
and pull the reverse hyper you know I've
got plate loaded deadlift apparatuses
the Hammer Strength I've got the pit
shark we do STI legs off that um and and
and all these gizmos too like our t-bell
and on the blocks are sliding leg for
the rolling the the the hammy track and
roller and all these cool things and you
can be
distracted because it's like you want
your hamstrings to grow try and get
really strong at stiff legs or you know
and then and then a leg seated leg cows
or something like so trust me I get it
but they're doing too much variety
they're not prioritizing Progressive
overload and PRS and doing all the
things necessary to give themselves the
best chance of pring like adequate sleep
adequate protein adequate optimal
calories Etc um sometimes you'll you'll
go to women and and kind of try to gauge
how much protein they're taking in
sometimes it's like they're eating 50
grams of protein in a day and they weigh
120 and they see great results when you
take that
to 90 100 110 120 130 they see better
results that way like some people it's
like magic um so yeah got to get so
inadequate
protein um inadequate sleep and stress
levels program hopping but the most is
lack of effort yep and trying to make up
trying to compensate with effort with
volume and variety and it doesn't it
doesn't compensate for it you can't just
do all the exercises and doing 20 sets
with five reps in the tank probably
doesn't beat doing one awesome set to
True failure and riding down in your log
book or on your app or in your notes on
your phone and then trying to beat it
cuz that requires a mental challenge too
when you know you've hip thrusted 315
for 15 and you're trying to get 20 and
you're like how the hell am I going to
get 16 and S how am I going to get to 20
and then you know you're hip thrusting
tomorrow you're going to be like okay I
better eat optimally today I better
sleep optimally today and what time am I
going to train tomorrow I I I'm going
for 16 this is going to be tough it's
hard to do and it doesn't always work
linearly like that it that's another
complication so that's why you have
variety because yeah you can't just go I
got 15 16 then 17 then 18 then 19 then
20 usually you get 15 and then you take
a big break and you do all the things
and then all a sudden you gear up for 20
again and it happens but yeah that's
another story so certainly There's
issues with effort right and I would
imagine that many people are trying
really hard but their efforts are
misplaced this is the example of doing
too many different things so lifting
maybe not lifting frequently enough
maybe not waiting long enough it's only
been a month right you need probably
several months or you're adding in
different forms of exercise and things
like that so you're trying really hard
your effort is super high but there's
not enough focus on stimuli to drive
that adaptation there's too much
distraction in the training right
another distraction you mentioned was
changing your programs too often right
so again this is where effort could be
High you could be really getting a burn
and really getting tired after the
workout but you did 50 different
exercises or you know you changed them
and because of that you probably
potentially did some maybe lower less
effective exercises your selection
wasn't great you were doing maybe all
body weight or all light bands and what
you're saying is you might be better off
picking one set of one exercise going
pretty heavy and then just getting out
of there right that would actually be a
a fun that would be hilarious to do like
a training study where you just have
them pick one set to go to F and then
you can do 15 sets we're not going to
track just do the Mind muscle connection
with those yep you know s feel the
squeeze feel the feel the the glutes
moving the weight but the that would be
a good system because it's hard when you
say progressive overload it's hard to
pin that down for people does that mean
mean do you go up on all four sets yep
do how do you go up another thing that
came to my mind here uh I don't know how
much you've experienced this or not in
terms of again let's think with the same
of I've tried to grow my glutes um by
the way I should interject here we've
been talking way more about the glutes
than I thought we were going to today
but you could change out glue for
anything else it doesn't actually matter
some of the details here do matter the
specific studies and the research and
and I'm going to ask here in a second
about how the glutes are different from
other muscles but I hope what you're
gleaning from this is not just only if
you're sitting here thinking I don't
care that much about glutes or whatever
this is scientific principles this is
how do you answer research questions
this is specific and precision right so
you're talking about not all exercises
are the same not all muscle groups are
the same we've dug in on the glutes so
again the answers might be different but
this is exactly how you should go about
answering it if you care more about the
triceps or the quads or the Cals or
anything else so this is a A system that
you developed over you know again almost
30 years now that can be applied to
anything else so I really hope that
people listening um are are gleaning
this out of it and going okay maybe you
do don't have some variation of love for
the glute but this is really the Nuance
that goes into to getting better results
for a very specific question uh that
you've really you know formulated a
career out of so hope that that message
is coming through if you enjoyed this
clip you can watch the full episode by
clicking here
[Music]